Guide to the Methodist Episcopal Church of Catharine records,1819-1882.
MethodistEpiscopal Church of Catharine records,1819-1882
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
MethodistEpiscopal Church of Catharine records, 1819-1882.
6082
Methodist Episcopal Church of Catharine (Catharine, N.Y.)
1 reel microfilm.
Microfilm.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
One volume of quarterly conference minutes for the Catharine Circuit (1819-1847), a class book for the first class in Johnson's Settlement (1833-1839) listing members' attendance, and a record book (1852-1882) of the Catharine Sunday School Association.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The Methodist Episcopal Society organized in 1805 met in private homes until 1809 when a church building was erected. In 1834 a new building was constructed. Catharine was the center of Johnson's Settlement which the records indicate was a pivotal charge on the Catherine circuit. At vaious times the circuit also included: Newtown (Elmira), Hector, McIntyre's Settlement, North Settlement, Newtown Creek, Jefferson, Veteran, Horseheads, Dean's Corners and Newfield.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
This collection consists of one volume of Quarterly Conference meeting minutes from the Catharine circuit (1819-1847), a class book for the first class in Johnson's settlement (1833-39), and a record book from the Catharine Sunday School Society (1852-1882).
SUBJECTS
Names:
Methodist Episcopal Church of Catharine (Catharine, N.Y.); Catharine Sunday School Association (Catharine, N.Y.); Johnson's SettlementCatharine, N.Y.
Subjects:
Church records and registers--New York (State)--Catharine.; Methodist Episcopal Church--New York (State)--Catharine.; Sunday schools--New York (State)--Catharine.
Places:
Schuyler County (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Catharine (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Minutes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Quarterly Conference meeting minute book, 1819-1847, Item #1
  Minutes record attendance (president, secretary, circuit preachers, local preachers, leaders and stewards), an accounting of money collected, baptisms performed (name, parents, date and place of birth, date and officiator of baptism), occasional resolutions and disciplinary cases and reports from Sunday Schools. Items of note include:
  - Inside Cover
    Subscription clips and a report of a baptism in 1797.
  - November 1819
    Minutes commence.
  - September 16, 1820
    Plans are made to provide a parsonage, (note: discussion of a parsonage and paying for it continue throughout most of the volume).
  - October 21, 1826
    Trial for abuse of family, lying and misrepresentation.
  - January 1827
    Resolved to join with the Ithaca Conference to hold a camp meeting in Danby on August 19th.
  - August 13, 1827
    Voted to accept the constitution of the Methodist Tract Society.
  - October 16, 1830
    Resolved that each class leader keep a subscription book of what each person pays.
  - October 16, 1830
    Resolved to form Sabbath schools at the different towns on the circuit if practicable. Br. Pearsall is appointed.
  - January 8, 1831
    Resolved to use the influence of the conference to enforce the observance of the Rule of Discipline related to the use of ardent spirits.
  - April 5, 1833
    Voted to hold a camp meeting with Southport, Painted Post and Elmira in Veteran in June.
  - January 1834
    No minutes. A list of classes with their contributions for 1834 follows (Appears regularly hereafter).
  - June 6, 1835
    First meeting at the new meeting house in Havana.
  - June 6, 1835
    Resolved that circuit preachers take collections for the support of missions.
  - March 19, 1836
    Request that the general conference restore Wesley's original rule in regard to the use of ardent spirits.
  - May 15, 1841
    Statement on discipline.
  - September 11, 1847
    Last entry.
  - Inside Cover
    History of a store in Catharine.
- Class book for the 1st Class in Johnson's Settlement for the year 1833", 1833-1839, Item #2
  The volume contains a numbered list of members and their state in church and society; includes: their state in life, and their attendance for specific dates (1833-1839). At the end of the volume there follows a list of subscriptions (n.d.) and a list of members received on trial.
- Sabbath School Record Book, 1852-1882, Item #3
  Includes constitution, by-laws and minutes of the Catharine Sunday School Association auxiliary to the Sunday School Union of the Methodist Episcopal Church. Annual minutes record the election of officers, the appointment of teachers, a financial report and the appointment and reports of committees.